<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second edition of the nevv almanack for the year 1656. Or, the nocturnall revised: being annotations upon the late Mercurius Aëro-machus. Wherein that author, or the printer for him, which is all one was very rightly mistaken, when he intituled the same a rel--i--ation of strange and wonderful sights seen in the aire on the first of January last, at the time the moon was in the eclipse. The truth whereof, if any man doubteth, it is but airing his horse in a morning or so, as far as Selby in Yorkshire, which is scarce an 150 miles off, where the print of the horses feet are still to be seen in the skie. Together with an huge compasse-window rainbow, seen that night at Jack-daw-ood, in the same countie; where the eccho of the drums and trumpets remian visibly to be heard to this day. Being likewise communicated in a letter to a friend, with an epistle dedicatory at the end of the book.</title>
            <author>Seaman, Henry, fl. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E490_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865248</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 78:E490[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second edition of the nevv almanack for the year 1656. Or, the nocturnall revised: being annotations upon the late Mercurius Aëro-machus. Wherein that author, or the printer for him, which is all one was very rightly mistaken, when he intituled the same a rel--i--ation of strange and wonderful sights seen in the aire on the first of January last, at the time the moon was in the eclipse. The truth whereof, if any man doubteth, it is but airing his horse in a morning or so, as far as Selby in Yorkshire, which is scarce an 150 miles off, where the print of the horses feet are still to be seen in the skie. Together with an huge compasse-window rainbow, seen that night at Jack-daw-ood, in the same countie; where the eccho of the drums and trumpets remian visibly to be heard to this day. Being likewise communicated in a letter to a friend, with an epistle dedicatory at the end of the book.</title>
                  <author>Seaman, Henry, fl. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Not in fact an almanac. Possibly a satire.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Seaman -- cf. Wing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Omens --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Satire, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Second Edition OF THE NEVV ALMANACK For the Year 1656. OR, THE Nocturnall Reviſed: Being Annotations upon the late <hi>Mercurius Aëro-machus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein that Author, or the Printer for him, which is all one, was very rightly miſtaken, when he Intituled the ſame A REL-I-ATION OF Strange and wonderful Sights ſeen in the Aire on the firſt of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> laſt, at the time the Moon was in the Eclipſe.</p>
            <p>The truth whereof, if any man doubteth, it is but airing his Horſe in a morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſo, as far as <hi>Selby</hi> in Yorkſhire, which is ſcarce an 150 miles off, where the print of the Horſes feet are ſtill to be ſeen in the Skie.</p>
            <p>Together with an huge Compaſſe-window Rainbow, ſeen that night at <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daw-ood,</hi> in the ſame Countie; where the Eccho of the Drums and Trumpets remain viſibly to be heard to this day.</p>
            <p>Being likewiſe Communicated in a Letter to a Friend, with an Epiſtle Dedicatory at the end of the Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:164053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:164053:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He nimble aiery Mercury, having gotten the ſtart of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator, that he could not be bound up with him; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether his treatiſe may ever come to your hands, for the better underſtanding of the <hi>Following premiſſes,</hi> I thought fit to give you in this page, in ſtead of the Actors names, a briefe account of the ſtory, without <hi>Interlarding,</hi> eſpecially of thoſe more remarkable paſſages, which are Anatomiſed and held forth in this Lecture.</p>
            <p>On Tueſday the firſt of Ianuary laſt, betweene 7 and <hi>8</hi> of the clock at night, the Moone being then in the Eclipſe, the aire very cold, but no wind at all ſtirring: The Author of that relation, with divers other ſpectators, diſcovered in the aire, towards the North-weſt, a certain ſtreame or cloud, in forme and colour like a Rainbow, which first paſſing away, there aroſe from the earth a bright and fiery pillar, ſtanding ſtraight up, but not very high: above this fiery pillar, there appeared a darkiſh cloude, out of which came a great company of Horſe and Foot, the which in a little time, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into a mighty army: ſo compleat for order, and other things, that the beholders, though many of them ſouldiers, ſaid, <hi>They never ſaw the like,</hi> and here you muſt be ſure to remember, that a Miniſter, in a marginal note of the book, telleth you, that he being <hi>a hanger on at that ſcuffle,</hi> verily thought that the forme of Battalia, reſembled that of Naſeby-field, as he remembreth to have ſeen the ſame ſet forth in mapps: <hi>Thoſe Gentlemen, having taken their ſeats,</hi> at the ſame time there appeared in the Eaſt another great army of Horſe and Foot: the which came out of the Earth as the former, but without the prologue of a pillar, and a cloud, <hi>They being not willing to goe to the charge</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:164053:3"/>
The Eaſterne army was greater in number, and bigger in bulke of body, then the other, but not ſo comely to ſight, nor any commander in chiefe therein nor ſomany field officers as the others had, who beſides, inferiour Captaines, had a Generall much like to the Sun: riding before them] Both the armyes marched one towards another, but it was obſerved, the North-weſt, <hi>[being perhaps a flying army</hi> went much faſter, and met the other the better half way being met, there happened a very formall and mortal battel betweene them, but in concluſion; the North west army beat the other out of the field, <hi>and yet durſt not keep it all night, themſelves for feare of an ambuſh,</hi> but went off too, And all this happened in a little more, then half an hower, and it is to be remembred, that when the North-weſt army, went off, the Priſoners that were taken, were plainly ſeen amongſt them, this ſight is ſaid to have been ſeen at <hi>wiſtoo</hi> neer <hi>Selby</hi> in Yorkshire.</p>
            <p>The ſame Night was ſeen a Rainbow too, at Hull.</p>
            <p>Alſo at <hi>Cawood,</hi> the ſame night, the like to all this was diſcovered by a Company, who were viewing the Eclypſe of the Moon: One of them <hi>being more quick-ſighted then any of the reſt,</hi> Firſt ſpying the Armyes in the Aire: ſhewed them afterward to his fellows; According to the old prouerb, <hi>One foole makes many.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164053:3"/>
            <head>THE LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the ſlender Ticket I bring with me for my admittance, you will eaſily perceive, how readily preſumptuous I am to intrude upon your more ſerious affairs, it being onely the incloſed printed paper; whoſe report, if in its paſſage up at firſt it <hi>blew the horn,</hi> or hath ſince reflected hence by other means unto you, I beſeech you to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don this abſurdity, and then impute the reaſon of my ſending, to be a deſire of knowing; whether this have any better credit with you, then that of vagrant ſame alone; or of the no leſſe impudent Preſſe, which though no gadder abroad it ſelf, hath ſtill ſtanding by it thoſe <hi>vomitum abſorbentes,</hi> as the Painter feigned of the Poet, ſuch as are ready to lick up any thing, and all it caſteth forth, that nothing be loſt: Not knowing where to finde the Author, who perhaps is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſick, <hi>poor man,</hi> with the fright he took; and therefore had not need be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed with queſtioning] I have preſumed to trouble you for my ſatisfaction, who I ſuppoſe may be able to give ſome certain account thereof, if any ſuch be to be expected; ſince I finde it, if not acted in, yet forged for your own meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; the very town, if I miſtake not, where ſome of your friends in the North dwell, and where they ſay this <hi>Terrible big-bellied-Trojan-horſe</hi> Cloud disburthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf, and afterwards packed up again, and went off with a very orderly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. As yet I muſt confeſſe I eſteem it but what the Author himſelf, without correction, hath Intituled it, A RELIATION indeed; that <hi>half-piked</hi> letter [though he intended to ſmother the buſineſſe; for fear it ſhould be chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged again] which he took up after the field was fought, being in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not redundant, but neceſſarily inſerted, whereby that word alone is rendred true, and all the whole Book beſides one great continued <hi>Erratum;</hi> which if ſo, the very Contempt thereof is puniſhment enough for ſuch a forgerie; <hi>Yet This fellow</hi> hath thereby ſo diſturbed, and moved the aire, that I cannot keep a Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill I have in my head from running Sallengers round, a while with it; but being yet at libertie, I ſhould be loath to immure my ſelf, as needs I muſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two walls; If I ſhould undertake to decide the nicety of the point in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral (waving in all reſpects the preſent Relation) whether Apparitions of this nature, have indeed ſo much reality in them, as that of their very apparency, or no, there being not more confident maintainers on the one ſide, then obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate oppoſers on the other; and therefore I ſhall decline the ſame, and confine my ſelf to ſit cloſe upon the skirts of my Author, making ſome proper Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon my preſent <hi>Don Quixot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, that there might bee no ſtop in proceedings, but that without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending your belief, you may be ready to <hi>Join iſſue</hi> with him, he telleth you he was preſent himſelf, an eie-witneſſe of the combate; and I think, with ſome ſmall neceſſary alteration, I might add for him what his own modeſtie would
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164053:4"/>not permit him to utter; <hi>viz.</hi> that great brag of <hi>Aeneas</hi> to <hi>Dido,</hi> in his ſtorie to her of the ſack of Troy. <hi>Et quorum pars tota fui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he was preſent, yes that he was, I will maintain it for him againſt any man; for he muſt needs be there, where he either ſaw or made this Tragedy: unleſſe we will fondly imagine the Seal can be abſent from the Wax, while the impreſſion is making; or that his Printer was drinking at the Ale-houſe, all the while his book was in hand: for my own part I ſhall eaſily believe him to have been preſent; And yet (if he aimed at that) think him never the more valiant; For though I aſſure my ſelf the ſtouteſt heart could not brook ſuch a ſight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome aſtoniſhment; yet I know no reaſon, but the ſhamefulleſt coward may ſtand by him too, cheek by jowl, with hazard little enough; however, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was there, for we muſt not imagine, that theſe new raiſed Train-bands, of the Rare-Aërian-militia, would go to exerciſe themſelvs in their <hi>Artillery-garden</hi> without giving notice to their <hi>Cozen citts,</hi> that ſo they might, if they pleaſed, be <hi>Spectators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus far I have engaged my Author; and yet further, if honeſt probable contrivance, &amp; ſelf-denying moderation, in what the Relator himſelf may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, as ſomtimes it doth; I know no reaſon but it may here as well win upon our belief; for though the publiſher (I will ſay that for him who ever he was) may be able no doubt to ſee as far into a mill-ſtone as another man, yet this <hi>Kitiſh Gipſie</hi> would not pretend to ſpie, or diſcover what theſe combatants did, untill they were come clear out of the cloud; And then I hope it was as lawful for him to take a view of them at full, as another man, which if he did, as he ſaith, <hi>pace tua Domine.</hi> it was long of your eies.</p>
            <p>Having thus far not onely vindicated, but commended our Author; I hope for my good will towards him, it will not be expected I ſhould anſwer for any of his after-failings, nor do I intend it; for I muſt needs confeſſe, I cannot clear him in one particular of the contrivance, as to point of prudence, whereof perhaps hee would purpoſely make no uſe, it being a <hi>Cardinal</hi> virtue; The matter is this: He fancied the Battalia form of the Armies he talketh of, to have <hi>reſembled thoſe real ones at Naſeby field</hi>] An error I did not think he would have been guiltie of, and for his credits ſake I would be loth any bodie elſe ſhould take <hi>notice</hi> of, I much wondering how he could poſſibly hope, this <hi>Retrograde Prognoſrication</hi> ſhould any way take with the people, in foretelling them a thing from the skie, that had been already paſt more then ten years: And ſurely if Aſtrologers are judged to ſoar too high by ſome, who make the Stars a prophetical book, legible to judgments that way ſtudied, yet this Reviſing Calculator to be ſure erreth as much in <hi>defectu,</hi> who offereth to make them his poſt-book and Chronicle, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to regiſter things already paſt, this in time might have been fairly provided for: If I had been of his counſel, I would have adviſed him to have winked at the buſineſſe <hi>a while,</hi> and have let the skirmiſhers fought on till the 12 of <hi>June,</hi> and then a bodie might have had ſomwhat to ſay for him; <hi>That probably,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſlain on both ſides, were anniverſarily allowed weapons on that day, to renew the memorie of their Combate. I will urge this ſlip no more upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher, it being more pardonable in him: <hi>But that the reverend Rabbi</hi> MANAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEH BEN ISRAEL <hi>too,</hi> ſhould be found not onely acceſſary, but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164053:4"/>in this foule miſtake, is a thing whereby I humbly conceive <hi>He hath deſerved to have his whole nation barred out of England,</hi> and that he ſhould conſent to have his follie hung up in the margent, like a <hi>head and purtenance,</hi> is ſuch a deſire of being taken notice of, I believe would ſet even the grave men of Gotham them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, into a very dangerous irrecoverable laughter. That all things might have been anſwerable, I once thought to have had this man in my margent too, but then I intended to have had him drawn at length in his own <hi>proper colours;</hi> in a pied Coat, and ſuch a like Sophiſters Cap, with his worthie obſervation written in a <hi>ſcrowl</hi> coming out of his mouth. Sir! your ingenuous confeſſion, that you onely make the compariſon as it lieth in the Map, not pretending you were at the fight your ſelfe, to have blown the coals. I approve of, and no man blameth you for your ſtudie of <hi>praelic-graphical maps,</hi> or that accurate <hi>Poſture-Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xicon;</hi> where we have the ſame man in ſeveral places, ſhouldring, loading, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, priming, and diſcharging his musket; no man blames you for this, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requiſite, that while ſo many ſouldiers in this later age have turned preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that ſome of theſe ſhould go over and fill up their ranks, that ſo in time, if ſo it come to paſſe, all on both ſides may be found to have changed ſtation. It being better ſo, for ought I know, then being ſhuffled into one pack of <hi>milito-prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicant</hi> Clergie, or <hi>praedico-militant</hi> Souldiery: nor can any impute to you as <hi>a Seer,</hi> your itching deſire of beholding this Ran counter. All this was well enough, but ſince you would needs have all things <hi>Hieroglyphical,</hi> nay and the very <hi>form</hi> of the Battel too: Yet ſure it had been more conſonant, eſpecially for <hi>You,</hi> to have patterned the reſemblance of the Battalia <hi>ex Sparta tua</hi> by ſome other Armies which the pillar and cloud, you all agree was there, might well have minded you of, but now to <hi>the Book</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>This ſight he telleth you was ſeene the <hi>firſt of January.</hi>] And now <hi>Janus</hi> his gates are thrown of the hinges, and we are like to haue a mad new yeare, which thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth with fighting for <hi>we muſt not thinke it will end thus.</hi> for if the weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers rule hold true, that a jury of holy-dayes are ſummoned every yeare to give vp their verdict of the following moneths; whether guilty or not of faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>whoſe corne,</hi> vpon what ground I know not, <hi>they meaſure by their owne buſhell,</hi> then I ſay, <hi>Raw-head and bloody bones,</hi> we muſt looke for terrible doings all next July, that being the ſeventh month, as well as new yeares day the ſeaventh feaſt from Chriſtmas; but againe I muſt remember you this firſt of January fell then on a Tueſday; for this tale would not haue been ſo proper if it had had fallen on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother day, it being very requiſite <hi>Mars his puppet play,</hi> ſhould be acted on his own holy-day. Beſides, it falling out ſo pat at that time of year; In my opinion it may paſſe for the prettieſt piece of <hi>Enthuſiaſtick Mummery,</hi> that ever was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, to entertain the time in a <hi>Chriſtmas Gamboile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author goeth on. <hi>Between</hi> 7 <hi>and</hi> 8 <hi>of the Clocke at night,</hi>] He is ſomewhat too preciſe in the time, which might give occaſion to ſome to thinke it a plo ted buſineſſe, but I am none of <hi>thoſe,</hi> For indeed I hold his diſcretion commendable therein, who judged that ſuch an antick maſke as this, would ſhew much better by <hi>owle-light.</hi> and therefore intending to have onely a few waxe candles and a torch or two to ſhew by, it is obſerved that after be had lighted them up, it being onely a private acting, that he put out the <hi>Moone</hi> taking her by the heeles; and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164053:5"/>holding her head a while under water, in the ducking pond, making them who ſtood by beleeue ſhe was burnt out and <hi>Eclypſed</hi> in a ſnuffe, there is a further rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſo late; <hi>Sed de hoc vide plura infra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There appeared ſaith he <hi>in the aire</hi>] Our relator I ſee is a very fair gameſter, and may be truſted another time, for though there was no-body there but himſelfe to eye him, yet he ſcorned to deale foule, playing all aboue board, <hi>vp in the ayre</hi> high enough to be ſure, he need not feare any body ſhould looke in his hand, for which perhaps he had a private reaſon to himſelfe, having been formerly, if ſame belie him not, burnt at ſeſſions for forging of <hi>debentares:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But againe <hi>In the aire</hi>] And why not I pray; you that giggle and fleere ſo at this? you would be loath in a winter night when you ſit poring in the chimney corner, and frame Chymaeras to your ſelſe out of the fire, that any body ſhould contradict what you proteſt you ſee there, while the <hi>night mare</hi> is upon you and the reſemblance holdeth ſtrong; and why then muſt this man be denied his <hi>Vis Plaſtica?</hi> being a man of very choice parts that way, as I preſage will hereafter be judged of him, when his body commeth to be begged for an <hi>anatomy;</hi> why then muſt he I ſay be denied either the power, only berty, of forming to himſelfe what fights he pleaſeth, of horſe, foot, armes &amp;c. out of the other Element? and truely in my opinion this <hi>maſter</hi> of the <hi>ceremonies</hi> deſerveth the monopoly better then any other, few beſides himſelfe being able to have marſhalled all things in ſuch excellent <hi>equipage</hi> as he hath done.</p>
            <p>There appeared in the <hi>Aire</hi> what? <hi>A certaine ſtreame or cloud ìn ferme and colour like a rainbowe</hi>] who can tell what to make of this? <hi>A certain ſtream or cloud? and onely like a rainbow?</hi> he aſcertaineth nothing, and yet if it reached from one end of the aire unto the other, as probably it did, I ſhall not doubt to affirme for him it was a meere <hi>Croſſe-Bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>paſſing away there aroſe</hi> &amp;c. the prologue being over, the play beginneth, enter the military pageant; but by the way hence may be collected that his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours were but poore ſpirited men, or but meanely accoutred with defenſive armes that they durſt not come upon the ſtage untill <hi>The coaſt was cleare,</hi> you had like to have ſeene none of them, vnleſſe the bowe be firſt removed (call and hang if you will) although it was certaine there was no body there but the man In the <hi>moone</hi> to ſhoot it of:</p>
            <p>But now they hunt full mouth, having ſtarted the hare: <hi>There aroſe from the earth ſaith our Author a bright and fiery pillar; on the top of this pillar was ſeen a cloud, out of this cloud came forth a long et cetera of horſe; foot, cannon, armes</hi> and what not? he now that thinketh theſe words are all to be underſtood, literally, I aſſure him will find himſelfe very much deceived. for <hi>Ut ſimiles haheant labra lactucas</hi> I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved <hi>ſomnium in ſomnio requiretur,</hi> to have my dreame and vagary as well as he; not caring though I thereby intangle the. buſineſſe ſo much the more, having provided as mad a comment for ſo mad a ſtory: <hi>The truth</hi> of the matter then was <hi>This,</hi> the relator hauing nothing elſe to doe, in an odde moode, <hi>obſerving his time, when the Moon was na pping,</hi> went and tranſferred Lets wife from the plaines of Sodome, placing her more advantageouſly uppon a riſing hill in York-ſhire; this is meant by his <hi>pillar,</hi> where when he had fixed her, looking a while, and peering very wiſhfully vpon her as e're Pigmalion on his ſtatue; at length <hi>Horrendum dictu</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:164053:5"/>from vnder her <hi>blacke hood,</hi> which he very ſubtilly termed a <hi>cloud,</hi> this muſter-maſter Generall eſpied theſe brave aerian duelliſts come crawling forth: nor doth it any way hinder this expoſition, that the Author expreſſely ſaith <hi>this pillar was on fire,</hi> for wee muſt know it is not ſaid to be ſo in reſpect of matter, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort, may be apt to take it, but in reſpect of the forme thereof; in that it went pointing and ſpiring vp like a flame, that ſo, let the matter haue beene what it would, yet ſtill it might have beene called fiery in reſpect of the <hi>Pyramidall</hi> forme thereof; but to ſatiſfy the further contentious I <hi>am reſolved it was and ſhall be ſo as I have ſaid</hi> and though I ſhould grant them it were true and reall fire. yet according to the rate that I intended to expound this treatiſe, it may ſtand well enough for ſalt too, and what is that to them, if the Author be content, to whom I thinke I haue done a courtefie, ſince ſuch ſtories as theſe vſe not to paſſe <hi>ſine grano ſalis</hi> and vnleſſe wee allow him ſome ſeaſoning for his fiery pillar it would preſently goe out in <hi>igne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the Learned: But that other people too may have ſomewhat for their money, I ſhall ſuppoſe the Riſe to have been this: For wee muſt know, <hi>That all fictions are built vppon ſome Fundamentall truth</hi>] Our Author as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, having been well warmed with a long winded mornings draught, which held him till two in the afternoon, laid himſelfe down upon the bed, where ſlumbring away ſome two or three houres, at laſt he fell into a ſound ſleepe; but being wakened on a fuddain, with a mighty noiſe over his head above in the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> he lay ſtill and harkned; but being much afraid, and judging the tumult rather to increaſe, he got him up, and went and raiſed the towne, when having] <hi>The conſtable</hi> with them, they ſtole up ſtaires, to ſee what was the matter; being come to the doore, they heard ſuch a confuſed noiſe of ſcratching, ſqueaking, grinning, mauwing, &amp;c. that they could not poſſibly deviſe, what ſhould be the buſineſſe: Having firſt demanded, yea and tried to have forced an entrance, as themſelues give out, to excuſe their <hi>fullneſſe of Courage,</hi> finding the doore faſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricado'd up, and all the crannies ſtuffed with well tempered ratſ-bane, they went up another payre of ſtaires, into the three-peny roome, being reſolved to ſee the fight <hi>what ever it coſt;</hi> where when they were come, they untiled the top of the houſe, when looking downe after all theſe paynes theſe <hi>Sceptickes</hi> ſaw the mortalleſt battell, that ever was ſought betweene a company of North-weſterne Catts, (whoſe feet were ſhod with Wallnut-ſhells, which cauſed the great noiſe) And an unruly rout of North-eaſt Ratts, which, as they truely report (for fear will make a man glad to ſay any thing) were much bigger then their Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But to be ſhort, the <hi>Cattae</hi> (being a very warlike people, who give the lyon rampant for their armes, being allowed by the Heralds ſo to do, for that as is found upon record, their <hi>Anceſtor</hi> was ſpitten out of his mouth) and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo in a juſt cauſe, to recover the Impery, nature had conferred on them over the other quickly ſubdued, and drave them all into a <hi>mouſe-hole:</hi> This latter opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion I rather incline to, for that I find it giveth light to the deciſion of a former queſtion <hi>viz.</hi> What that <hi>ſtreame or cloud in forme and colour like a Rainbow</hi> ſhould be, which wee were fain to ſtubber over before it was no other then the beam that went croſſe the room where they fought; Which being in a Gentlemans houſe, was painted all over of a light red colour: onely here and there a ſtreak
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164053:6"/>of green and white, and other colours, <hi>even as pleaſeth the Painter;</hi> you may laugh at this now if you pleaſe: but I aſſure you as well skilled in <hi>Horſ-fleſh,</hi> as the beſt of you are; the beam being arched, and coloured, as it was, you might have been deceived thereby, as well as our Author. The next thing we obſerve unto you is the <hi>great Number</hi> of both armyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Severall companies of Horſe and Foot,</hi> &amp;c.] Now if any man on purpoſe to cavill, after ſo manifeſt conviction ſhould yet peeviſhly examine, how ſo many regiments of Horſe and Foot, carriage, Baggage, Ammunition, &amp; all Habiliments of war, neceſſary to the furniſhing forth a royal army, for a pitched field) could all be contained, &amp; lie dormant, like <hi>Jack in a box</hi> under ſo little a Hovel as the Cloud he ſpeaketh of, which in reaſon could not be very big, ſince being fixed on the pillar, it would well nigh have obſcured the ſame; it being not very high, which yet was not ſo?) <hi>Our relator,</hi> hath herein to anſwere for himſelfe, for ought I know, what a former <hi>Brother</hi> of his cloath was faine to make uſe of, when having confidently reported here at home, that beyond ſea there were Bees as big as Hogs, &amp; yet the hives no bigger then here in England; being thereupon demanded, how it was poſſible thoſe ſwiniſh bees could get in or out thoſe hiviſh ſties; flearingly replied, <hi>Nay let them looke to that;</hi> But not to put you off with a <hi>flam,</hi> nor yet to tell you the clouds are made of ſtretching Leather, whoſoever giveth credit to the ſtory of the Platter-faced Cabbage, which I hope wee all doe, who are not quite out of love with that Beef-ſauce-budget-root diſh, can no way doubt of the truth of this; ſince, for ought we know, the pillar was hollow, and where I pray then is the impoſſibility? This cloud on the top of the pillar, being then but as a <hi>round hole</hi> in the floor of a theater, whereat there being through vaults underneath, all the men in the citie might come up, If there were room as here there was to be ſure the whole aire being allowed them, for their <hi>Randezvous:</hi> But to leave no ſcruple, and fetch the author of cleare, without ranſome, what wil you ſay If I can prove, they all came out of a much leſſer place then the Cloud? And that is out of the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors owne noddle, the truth hereof if any man doubteth, I wil undertake for your two pence a piece, <hi>Come when you will,</hi> you ſhall ſee him ſend forth ten times as many more; give him leave to whiffe but a little Spaniſh firſt, which is but reaſon and then you ſhall plainly perceive the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Cloud</hi> he talketh of, were no other, but the <hi>lighted Tobacco-pipe</hi> he held in his hand: while at the ſame time he blew the <hi>Smoake</hi> out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This pillar and cloud it is ſaid, came out of the earth]</hi> out of the earth? hold a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: oh oh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the tune of <hi>Joy come to thee old Dicke,</hi> I haue now found who theſe gentlemen ſhould be: doe you not remember, how at the beginning of theſe times there was much talk, of great numbers of papiſts and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, who were trayning themſelues vnder ground, for a deſigne, which but ſome <hi>five men</hi> knew of, who had been dead fifty yeares before? and though ſome few foole-hardy infidells of that age, would not ſuffer themſelves to be gulled into a beleefe thereof, yet the event now hath proved it too true; <hi>Theſe were the men:</hi> but then a grand doubt will ariſe how our author brought theſe blades to his lure; for that ſide being wholly defeated, whoſe part they were to haue taken, they grew ſullen and intended never to have come out at all, And to thinke of forcing them was an idle enterpriſe, eſpecially the Caves mouth where they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164053:6"/>went in being altogether vnknowne, but our Author was no foole, for he had a <hi>tricke</hi> for this too, which he formerly learned when he was prentice to a <hi>wine Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> who have a pretty art, by knocking their knuckles on a wine veſſell to tell whether it be empty or not, and more then that, can force out the liquor into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother veſſell, without ever broaching, or powring it forth at the top; well then <hi>Our Author</hi> having formerly ſatiſfied himſelfe, where their <hi>Center</hi> was, which he accidentally diſcovered ſeven yeares agone, when he was faſt ſleeping on the ground, by a palpable noiſe which he heard in the <hi>roome vnderneath</hi> him, which he kept to himſelfe: <hi>But now</hi> on the firſt of January betimes in the morning; hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received an expreſſe from his <hi>Socio-forger</hi> in the North eaſt army, for betweene theſe two vſed to paſſe intelligence] that they were already upon the borders, and intended to be that night, at the place appointed betweene them for battell. This wine-Couper as I told you, taketh his Gamlock-pipe And goeth to his old <hi>Molehill</hi> where he had formerly ſlept, claweth of the bung with both hands And thruſting in his inſtrument a good way downe into the earth, which he found hollow, being a good-ſmith-bellow-lung'd Ruccinator, He ſent ſuch a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Alarme,</hi> into thoſe low ſubterraneous cavernes, That <hi>ne detur Vacuum,</hi> as the old bookes have it. But I rather, thinke for that they could not poſſibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his <hi>ſtinking breath</hi> came bolting vp, in order as they ſtood next theſe brave warriours Lees and all, not ſo much as a <hi>Landabrides</hi> being left behind; and here you muſt call to mind that all this was not done till between 7 and 8 at night, for which I promiſed to give you a further reaſon: Our Author would be loath to be found guilty of his ſlippe, who made <hi>Hercules</hi> bring vp <hi>Cerberus</hi> from Hell at noon day, when being un-uſed to the light, that Triple-headed, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>Twelve legged</hi> curre, ſtumbled three times every ſtepp he went, and was ready to knocke at leaſt one of his Choppes againſt every poſt he met; this was a pretty tolerable fore caſt,</p>
            <p>One gueſs more what Creatures theſe parties ſhould be, &amp; I have done: It being <hi>in the aire</hi> where they fought, I beleeve they were no other then two great ſwarmes of bees, ſtriving for the propriety of ſome <hi>Roſemary hangings</hi> growing on a wall, in the Relators garden: And if wee take it thus, wee muſt underſtand, that the pillar and cloud from whence they came, were no other, then the <hi>Hive</hi> and <hi>candle</hi> burning in it, to ſhew them the way out, it being then darke, And then too the Author might very well have intituled his ſtory, The Hiſtory of the <hi>Maccabees:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this were well enough: But did ever man talke more idly, when he telleth us of the approach of the armies each to other: <hi>It was obſerved</hi> ſaith he, that the <hi>North weſt army moved much ſwifter, and met the other more then halfe way:</hi> could he not be content to play the foole to himſelfe, but he muſt needs pull paſſengers by the cloake with an <hi>It is obſerved,</hi> who otherwiſe might happily not have taken notice of his folly? for if there be any, he himſelfe muſt beare the blame, ſince he brought the North weſt army in a <hi>coach</hi> to the place of battell, dropping them freſh and luſty out of his <hi>cloud</hi> as Cheſſe-men out of a bag and therefore no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if happily they were nimbler for a ſpurt then the other, who had come a long march that day, <hi>Having neither pillar nor cloud to eaſe them</hi>] in a direct line from the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> being faine to be their owne pioneers all the way: And yet for all his talke I beleeve if the truth were knowne, neither army had the <hi>ball</hi> of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164053:7"/>other, nor perhaps the <hi>goal,</hi> but that the Relator out of great partiality gave them both to the North-weſt Army; For though I know no reaſon, but he ought to have ſtood equally affected; <hi>They being both alike, his own offspring,</hi> yet ever ſince the <hi>Declaratorie Bull</hi> of the old Parlament againſt Neutralitie, he is reſolved to be of one ſide or other, and take to a <hi>Faction,</hi> although in a <hi>Fiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Eaſtern Armie had no Commander in chief, but the North-weſt had, and him a gallant perſon, like the Sun</hi>] Mounted upon a dark brown <hi>Barbary Pegaſus,</hi> who having a Scymitar in one hand, and a <hi>Caemiterium</hi> in the other, to bury therein all he ſhould kill, rode up to the front of the enemie, and fought there all the while, which was I conceive a chief cauſe the other were beaten, fighting at very great diſadvantage, <hi>having the Sun in their faces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fight continued halfe an hour]</hi> How, no longer? I wonder where this fellow got the nack of diſpatching buſineſſes of this nature in ſuch a trice: What! Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpread? gueſts come? a running banquet? all either eaten or pocketed up, and then the Bells rung backward, Cloath taken away! Company gone! yea and room ſwept too, that <hi>no bodie can tell any bodie was there,</hi> and all this in leſſe then an houre? Sure this was a rare Engineer: <hi>Ovid!</hi> why he was a fool to him in this kinde. What a ſtrange circuit doth he fetch to bring in his ſimple tale <hi>De fratribus denti-natis?</hi> Firſt we muſt hear a tale of a Cock and a Bull, in which laſt ſhape (a likely matter) <hi>Jove</hi> beareth away <hi>Cadmus</hi> ſiſter; and we, as if we had nothing elſe to do, muſt go ſeek her with him, till at laſt we finde her in the ſhape of a Cow; it was a wonder, having been ſo long away, ſhe had not a <hi>Calſe by her ſide</hi> too: And then again, after many more preambles, trots, gallops, and now and then a Parenthetical hedg and ditch to take over, at length he bringeth us to the place where <hi>Cadmus</hi> was to fight with the Serpent, which me thinketh, if the Poet would have done any thing for him, he might have got knocked down ready to his hands: However with much adoe, he and <hi>Cadmus</hi> together make a ſhift to kill the Dragon, and having boned his jaws, he perſwadeth this <hi>Wiſe-acres</hi> to ſow the ground with the teeth, which having done, he rocketh him aſleep in a cradle till harveſt, where he might have ſnoared till this time, but that he was wakened with a uery ſtrange confuſion, <hi>His new crop of corn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen together by the ears,</hi> and ſo continued threſhing one another a pretty ſpace in his ſight, till a ſtrong gale of winde laid them all one way; for that <hi>Cadmus</hi> eloquence did it I will never believe: he might well have ſpared ſome of this <hi>Preface,</hi> and not have omitted as he hath done, becauſe he could not get them into Verſe, ſome more remarkable paſſages, which yet I am fure are as true as moſt of the reſt; As that this Fray went afterwards by name of the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Cock-all;</hi> and that thereupon <hi>Cadmus</hi> inſtituted that antient <hi>Olympick</hi> game called <hi>Scale-pins,</hi> in memorie of nine of thoſe gallants Lads, who were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by themſelvs as a reſerve, in ſuch admired poſture, that look which way you would, rank, file, or croſſe, they ſtill were ſeen three, three and three, all <hi>Dactyle</hi> feet, like the beginning of the firſt verſe in <hi>Virgil, Ty-ty-re-tu-pa-tu-lae-re-cu-;</hi> which goodly order they maintained, till an hand-<hi>Granado,</hi> Anglice a <hi>Bowl,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately lighting among them, tipped them all down at once. I could have ſhewen this Poet a ſhorter cut; for if he muſt needs have his men without either fleſh or blood, for the more likelihood of the ſtorie, and better enduring the ſhock
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164053:7"/>of the battel, he might but have gone to one or two of our <hi>London</hi> Teeth-chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, &amp; have taken whole buſhels of this <hi>Bone-ſeed</hi> upon his word, or at moſt there needed but a deed of bargain and ſale have paſſed between them, which might very properly have begun with the uſual form of <hi>This Indenture,</hi> &amp;c. This had been the nearer way; for then being ready ſtrung, rank and file, to his hands; he needed but have ſent them into the liſts, they having a long time ſtood ready <hi>drawn,</hi> expecting when the word ſhould have been given: But what do we talk of him for! <hi>Our Author</hi> I am ſure would have taken this courſ, if he had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any ſuch mockery: But he thanketh you, he will not be perſwaded to venture his teeth to <hi>Dantzick</hi> in hopes of I know not what return, nor yet to bury them alive in the earth, before he goeth thither for good and all; as much doubting, I cannot blame him, whether ever they might ſpring up again. But if he muſt needs ſow before reap, he is for a <hi>crop of Muſhroms,</hi> ſomwhat that will come up again quickly, all in a night, that he may be ſure of his breakfaſt the next morning; <hi>And this method he uſeth in This invention.</hi> But that you may know I am as good at it as he, I will contract all in a leſſe compaſſe, and yet put in ſomwhat that he left out, <hi>Our Landlord</hi> then, on the firſt of the laſt January, having been very melancholie many daies before, and ſworn to ſee ſomwhat that night, what ever came of it; between 7 and 8 a night, having cleared his eie-ſight, and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his common ſence with a good round Boul of <hi>muddi-cappado,</hi> he ſteppeth me forth from the fire ſide into his yard, where having ſeated himſelf upon a <hi>three-ſtoried</hi> horſe-block, which ſtood juſt by the pales; the aire being very cold, that he could not poſſibly ſtay long out, preſently by the word of command, ſtarteth out a pillar from under the earth, as nimbly as ever <hi>Hiccius doctius</hi> out of <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> cap: on the top of this pillar was ſeen a Cloud, out of this Cloud came forth an innumerable company of Souldiers, who being all in a trice ſet in order, <hi>without any ſpeech at all made by the General to encourage them,</hi> they march towards another armie, which were ſeen coming on from an oppoſite quarter; ſtreight they meet, encounter, rout, kill, vaniſh, and all is well again; <hi>why now!</hi> is not this better then to beheld in ſuſpence as long as a man hangeth in chains? To be racked with tedious expectation? to be fed with news like Apes, a bit and a knock? <hi>As this day came intelligence of a great defeat given by our forces to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: next Poſt telleth us of numerous Recruits come to their Camp, whereby we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the near; and ſo the whole year ſpendeth, ſomtime our owne, ſomtime the enemies Army declining engagement.</hi> What fooliſh dallying is this? Is this man-fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? or not rather child-play? For my part, If when we are well we cannot be content, let us go to it quickly, <hi>agree who ſhall cut firſt,</hi> fight it out as theſe lads did, and ſo the <hi>laſt man take all:</hi> You are like to hear no more of theſe men I dare ſay, for our Author is no <hi>Cunctator Fabius,</hi> get the better who could, for he would not build any Caſtles in the aire for either ſide to retreat to; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my part, if ſuch a thing muſt needs be, I am of of our Authors minde, <hi>The ſooner over, the better;</hi> for though this <hi>Bear-heard</hi> did not well indeed to ſet theſe people together by the ears, yet he ſomwhat mended the matter, in ſtepping in with his Jacobs-ſtaffe ſo ſoon as he did, and parting them: but then again, hee did very ill, to report as he doth, that one ſide had ſo much the better of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For I ſpake with two or three of the North-eaſt Armie, who ſay, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164053:8"/>though they ſeemed indeed at firſt to be worſted, <hi>Their noſes being more ſubject to bleeding then other mens,</hi> yet they made no queſtion, as having, they were ſure, the longer breath, but to have beaten the other in the end, would this ſpectator but have let them alone; which if I had been He, they ſhould never have feared: <hi>But the truth is,</hi> there was ſomwhat in the winde with our Author, though he very cun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ningly would ſeem to anticipate any ſuch, objection in laying down, <hi>There was then no winde at all ſtirring,</hi> yet he being very much afraid at the horrible product of his own fancie, having ſufficiently <hi>Atkinized</hi> himſelf at this General Training, he was glad to lay the ſpirits, and huſh all up again in quiet; in which <hi>ſweet pickle,</hi> marvel not that I leave him, and have no more to do with him.</p>
            <p>And now put all this together: <hi>The unheard of approach,</hi> and unexpected arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, of theſe forces, being never before ſo much as dreamed of; <hi>The cauſleſſneſſe</hi> of their quarrel, who for ought we yet hear, It being then Eclipſe, fought onely as they ſay for <hi>Moonſhine:</hi> The <hi>place</hi> of combate in another guiſe ground then Callis ſands, <hi>up in the aire:</hi> A brave open Country; <hi>The certain cruelty of their fight</hi> ſhooting Starres againſt one another as faſt as hopps, and making all the kennels in <hi>via Lactea,</hi> run with blood; And yet at laſt, which is the wonder of all, <hi>The Harmleſſe Concluſion</hi> of the whole, it being more then probable, there was never a man Killed? And then tell me, If ever you heard of ſuch a Tragae-Comoediall Romance</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>THE POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu may ſee, though I ſay it; That I have been very merciful to theſe Armyes, having onely culled a paſſage, or two out of every Regiment, and made them ride the <hi>Wooden-Horſe;</hi> For a terror to the reſt, All of them having deſerved to be hanged for fighting without <hi>Order</hi> from the Councel of Warre: It had been very eaſie for me to have enlarged my <hi>Commentary,</hi> but that I have exceeded my Authors Volume: But by this taſte you may perceiv, what a rare ſubject this would have been, if ſome Learned <hi>Wire-drawer,</hi> or more refined neat-fingred <hi>Spinſter</hi> would have pleaſed to have taken it in hand: For I wil ſay that for our Author, and <hi>a fig for him,</hi> Though he be no very good worker up; yet he can cut out more in one hower then ten Journey-men are able to perfect in a month, or perhaps <hi>ever make good.</hi> Vale.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <head>A Liſt of ſome Officers names, of the North-eaſt Army, who were taken Priſoners by the enemy, for though the relator ſaith they had no Officers at all: Yet we are to take no great heed to that: Nor doe I charge a direct falſity herein, upon our Author, for wee cannot reaſonably imagine how he ſhould well diſcerne them from common Souldiers: or indeed from any thing elſe, at ſo great a diſtance; And that there were ſome taken Captives; Himſelfe expreſſely declareth.</head>
            <p>INprimis, Major Generall <hi>Wag-Staffe,</hi> not he that danced the Corranto laſt, care in the Weſt: nor any thing of Kinne to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lievtenant Colonell Shake-ſpeare.</hi> A very redoubted Commander.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:164053:8"/>
               <hi>Mounſieur Through-Goe-Nimble:</hi> A French man, Generall of the Horſe; Who Charged three times (After the rate of of ten Mile an hower,) Through all the North-weſt Cavalry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Splay-foote, Ten-toes</hi> Collonell of a Regiment of foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Gunner,</hi> Maſter of the Ordnance:</p>
            <p>Captaine, <hi>A' la mort</hi> Taken in the heate of the fight; Having been ſent the Night before, with an expreſſe: <hi>And not as yet returned;</hi> to give notice of the neere approach of the armyes; And to haſten the comming up of ſome Forces: who were already drawen out in Battalia; <hi>In the place,</hi> where the Battell was ſought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enſigne Scot, a Welſh man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>Major Spruce.</hi> A young Gallant who came thither to have his haire pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and get holes boared in his eares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Author</hi> himſelfe too, in the reare, being Secretary Generall to a Corporall of Dragoones; But ſince had his liberty for reporting the buſineſſe, ſo much to the advantage of his Enemies; As he doth in his relation.</p>
            <p>All theſe, together with ſeverall other <hi>The ſame Perſons,</hi> whoſe names are not yet certified; Are now Cloſe priſoners, In <hi>Concavo Lunae.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatorie.</head>
            <head type="sub">To his Honored Friend— in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Umpatur quiſquis, &amp;c.</hi> I am reſolved with your leave, to have my own way in doing here as I do; for though ſome may think me mad for giving ſuch hold againſt my ſelf, in caſe the Relator ſhould reply; who perhaps will indite me of <hi>falſe Heraldrie,</hi> for laying Epiſtle upon Epiſtle, (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I once heard him argue the caſe very learnedly with a Carpenter, who was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Wicket in the middle of a great Gate) or which is as bad, ſend ſome Pedagogue with his <hi>ferula</hi> in his hand, to challenge me with a falſe Poſition, in placing this <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Preface,</hi> in manner as I have done; yet I fear him not, let him do his worſt: Be you Sir pleaſed to accept of it <hi>vultu annuente,</hi> it being made, I aſſure you, while I my ſelf was nodding, <hi>inter</hi> ſleeping <hi>&amp;</hi> waking, neither one nor other; which you will the rather believe by what followeth, having, I proteſt unto you, been once ſuch a fool as to dream, I muſt needs be reciting this May-game in your Schools at the next enſuing Act: And that you may know I tell you no tale, I ſtill remember ſome of the <hi>Compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorie Introduction,</hi> me thoughts I then uſed, which here you have. <hi>Reverendiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime Procancellarie, cum toto doctoratus ſatellitie, hî ovium, caprorum illic, in utramque manum aſſidentium. Patres, viri, juvenéſque Academici,</hi> and ſo wiſhing them all good reſt, I proceeded; <hi>Mihi diutius excogitanti, qualem anſam, ſolennitatem veſtram excipere, arrepturus eſſem, arriſit tandem Novus noſter Gallo-belgicus, quae nunc in toto notiſſima fabu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a coelo eſt:</hi> And then propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my queſtion, which you know I muſt of neceſſity do, ſome one or other, I took this,
<pb facs="tcp:164053:9"/>
               <hi>Omne gliſcens non eſt aurum;</hi> made uſe of my Author as a <hi>medium,</hi> and ſo went on <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> animadvertizing upon his relation, <hi>Licet non omnino ſecundum ſormam ſtatuti,</hi> which forbiddeth all Angliciſmes: Mine <hi>therefore</hi> being almoſt every word Engliſh, and yet I aſſure you, for thoſe two or three Tipps of the other Neats-tongue, which you finde therein, it had like never to have ſeen the light, if the zealous Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner who printed the other, could have helped, it being a main reaſon why he refuſed to put forth this too himſelf, whereof I afterward underſtood the cauſe; for that he being a <hi>Fifth-monarchie</hi> man, could not away with the language of the <hi>Fourth.</hi> I never intended to have printed it at all, but that it being Term-time, there was never a Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or Lawyers Clerk in Town at leiſure to write it out. (The Relator, if you ſee him, perhaps will tell you this was a lie to his knowledg, but believe him not) And for mine own part, I think it no ſhame to profeſſe, I can neither write nor read, ſo that it could not be otherwiſe engroſſed. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe near Strand-bridg</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. <hi>26. 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
